<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here be certayne questyons of kynge Bocthus of the maners, tokyns, and condycions of man, with the answeres made to the same by the phylosopher Sydrac</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16267</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110742</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846227</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846227</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11180</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16267)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11180)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 26:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here be certayne questyons of kynge Bocthus of the maners, tokyns, and condycions of man, with the answeres made to the same by the phylosopher Sydrac</title>
                  <author>Boccus, King.</author>
                  <author>Sidrac, 13th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by me Robert Wyer, dwellynge at the sygne of S. Ioh[a]n Euangelysts in S. Martyns Parysshe besyde Charyngs Crosse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1550]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A different text from STC 3188a.</note>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Questions and answers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11180:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11180:1"/>
            <p>¶ Here be Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Queſtyons of Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge Bocthus of the maners / tokyns / and condycions of man / with the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres made to the ſame by the Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher Sydrac.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <byline>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </byline>
                  <figDesc>divinely inspired colloquy</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:11180:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the philosopher Sidrak</figDesc>
                  <head>Sydrac.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of King Bokkus</figDesc>
                  <head>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Kynge.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise_on_physiognomy">
            <pb facs="tcp:11180:2"/>
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked by what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners / tokyns / and faſſyon myghte a man knowe the maners and condycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of good folkes and of euyl. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drac. Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. ☞</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the Grace and wit that god hath gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen vs, we ſhall ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we you ſhortlye the maner, by the which ye may well know the condycions of folkes, when yeſe and be holde them by ſome tokens y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall haue in them, for it is a thynge ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytable &amp; trewly proued, for there are maners and condycions in fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes. As the grayne is within the fruyte, that no man may well ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke it away but he bruſe the fruyt
<pb facs="tcp:11180:3"/>and breake it, and euen ſo it is of dyuer Folkes.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The kynge aſked what betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it of a man that is whyte ſkynned and frekened. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drac. Anſwered.<lb/>☞☜</head>
               <p>¶ He that is whyte ſkynned and the moſt parte frekened and gray iyen, it betokeneth a man to be ſhamefaſt and of good fayth. And euery man ought to kepe hym fro the ſyght of hym that is all freke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And yf he haue a large fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed, and a lytell chyn and great iowes, and the body all frekened, and moche and thycke heer on his heed, haunc not to moche his com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panye, nor medle but lytell with hym, for and thou do he wyll gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the. ☞</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11180:3"/>
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what token is it when a man hath the heer of his heed ſofte. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ A man that hathe ſofte heer on his heed, it betokeneth, that his brayne is colde, &amp; by reaſon they ought to be curtoyes and of lytell vnderſtandynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth it of a man that hath moch heer on his breſt and on his bely. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ They that haue moche heer on theyr breſt, and on they bellyes, it betokeneth that they that is ſo / ſhulde be of dyuers and wylde ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners, &amp; of lytell vnderſtandyng, &amp; ſhulde loue wel to do men wronge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11180:4"/>
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth whan a man hath mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che heer on his browes. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ He that hath moch heer on his browes, by reaſon ſhulde be boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtous in his dedes and langage, &amp; he that hath them ſmall and lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples ſhulde be dyſdayg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nous, &amp; he that hath the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſmal egal blacke, &amp; longe, he ſhulde be wroth full, and of great vnderſtandyng. And he that hath but lytell heer on his browes by reaſon ſhulde be lyght and peſyble.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſhed what to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens is there or mens iyen. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ The iyen of Men hath tokens that lye not, by a mans iyen a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11180:4"/>may ſe the pleaſour and the good wyll or the euyll wyll that a man oweth another, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath the iyen great &amp; graye withoute any ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes by reaſon ſhuld be ſlowthfull, anuyous and dyſdeynous. And he that hath his iyen mediat neyther to great nor to ſmale and not is graye but betwene both, he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perte and dylygent &amp; of good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandynge and loueth trouth. And he that hath the iyen redein his lokynge, By reaſon he ſhulde be bolde and a great medler, and yf he haue about the appull of the iyen yelow ſpottes, it is the worſt toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that may be of all the tokens of the iyen. And when ye ſe a man that beholdeth and loketh often on you, boldelye loke on hym alſo agayne. And yf ne be ſhamefaſte and blenche his ſyght from you, and he appereth as a man that
<pb facs="tcp:11180:5"/>laugheth, &amp; not by his good wyll, and his iyen waxeth full of water that ye maye ſe the teares of his iyen, that man loueth and dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth you. And yf any man loke on you and you on hym and he loke ſtedfaſtly and boldly on you &amp; blen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth not, nor is not a drede nor a ſhamed to loke on you, that man hathe enuye at you, and neyther doughteth nor loueth you. And be well ware and truſte hym not, and kepe you well from all euyll auentured creatures, as yf ye wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de kepe you from youre deedlye Ennemyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked howe ſhulde a man knowe, another by the tokens of his noſe Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ He that hath the noſe lytel and
<pb facs="tcp:11180:5"/>ſmall he loueth ſtryfe and debates and he that hath the noſe longe tyll the mouth he by reaſon ſhulde be manlye. And he that hath his noſe ſnatted and great / he ſhulde be coueitous. And he that hath lar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge nooſe thrylles ſhulde be wrath full &amp; full of yre. And he that hath the noſe great, and moſt greateſt in the myddes, by reaſon ſhulde be a great lyer And he that hath the no emedyat, neyther to great nor to ſmall, nor to longe nor to ſhorte, and his noſe thrylles not large, he by reaſon ſhulde be wyſe and of good vnderſtandynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what tokens ſhulde a man haue by another mannes forheed. Sydrat. Anſwereth.</head>
               <p>¶ He that hath the forheed large
<pb facs="tcp:11180:6"/>and not fulle of ryuell nor longe rayes, he is dyſceyuable and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth guyles and barrattes, and alſo he is enuyous. And he that hath the forheed not to large but medyatly betwene two, by reaſon ſhulde be trew, louynge, wyſe, and well doctryned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what token is there of a mannes lyppes. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ He that hathe great lyppes is is rude, and ſhulde be of harde vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtandynge, and he that hathe them mediat neyther to great nor to ſmalle, he ſhulde by reaſon be ryghte temperate in his wyttes and dedes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what token is there of a mannes mouth. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:11180:6"/>
               <p> ¶ He that hath the mouth reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble large, by reaſon ſhuld be man lye. And he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath a lytell ſtreyght mouthe by reaſon ſhuld haue but lytell fayth, and as lytell wyt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, what token is there to know a man by his teth. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ He that hath the teth wellioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and thicke ſet togyther by rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon he ſhoulde be mouable in his courage, and no man may be ſure of hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked by what to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſhall a man knowe another by his vyſage. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ When a mans vyſage is great and full, by reaſon he ſhulde be of
<pb facs="tcp:11180:7"/>rude nature, and he that hath the vyſage ſcryte and lene and yelowe browne, by reaſon he ſhulde be ſlye and cunnynge of all thynges that he medleth withall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken is there to knowe a man by his eares. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ When a man hath great eares it betokeneth rudeneſſe and boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuouſnes. And he that the eares paſſynge lytell ſhulde by reaſon be a fole and wrathfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what token is there to knowe a man by his voyce and ſpeche. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drac. Anſwered.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:11180:7"/>
               <p> ¶ He that hath the voyce and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che great and Rounde he ſhuld be manly. And who ſo euer hath the voyce temperat / neyther to great nor to ſmall he ſhulde be of great knowledge and trew. And he that hath the voyce paſſynge ſmall, he ſhulde be haſtye and a lyer. And he that hath the voyce paſſyng great he ſhulde be of euyll manners and of condycions ſlyght. And he that hath the voyce fayre and clere, he is of great vnderſtandynge and of great courage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens it when a man hath a longe necke. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ He that hath the necke longe &amp; ſmall, by reſon he ſhulde be full of foly, noyſe and cowardyſe. And he
<pb facs="tcp:11180:8"/>that hath a lytell heed ſhulde be a foole. And he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath a great heed ſhulde be rude and a great eater.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what toke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken is there of a mannes Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ He that hath a great Belye out of me ſure, he ſhulde be rude, and by reaſon a cowarde and not wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. And he that hath a ſmall belye and well breſted, he ſhulde be well wytted and of trewe counſayle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what token is there of a mannes Chynne and of his ſhulders. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ He that hath the chynnelarge, and his ſhulders large he ſhulde be manly, myghty and not of gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at
<pb facs="tcp:11180:8"/>wyt. And he that hath the chyn and the backe well furnyſſhed, he ſhulde be fyers and wrathfull. ☞ And he that hathe the Chynne ſtreyghte and egall, it is a ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge of goodnes. And he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath hye ſhulders is of euyll wyll and dyſdaygnous.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what token is there to knowe a man by his armes. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ He that hath longe armes that come to his knees, by reſon he ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de haue a free herte and a noble. And he that hath his armes paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge ſhorte, by reaſon ſhulde be a cowarde and lone noyſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates. ☞</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:11180:9"/>is there to knowe a man by his handes. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ He that hath longe handes and fyngers, by reaſon ſhulde do well all craftes and betrewe. And he that hath the palme of his hande ſofte ſhulde be wyſe and of good vnderſtandyng. And he that hath the handes paſſynges ſhorte and the fyngers ſhorte, he ſhulde not be very wyſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what token is there to knowe a man by his feet. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ He that hath his feet ſhort and greate, ſhulde haue lytell vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge and not wyſe. And he that hath his feet ſmalle aboute
<pb facs="tcp:11180:9"/>the ancle, he ſhulde be a cowarde. And he that hathe great feet and his legges great in the myddes / he ſhulde be bygge of bodye / but he ſhulde be rude and boyſtous.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynke aſked, what to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens haue ye of them that be gelded. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ He that is Gelded by mannes hande, he ſhulde be very wrothfull and falſe. And he that hath ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtones nor berde, he is an euyl ſayer and a lyer. And yf he be fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened alſo, he is enuyous and of euyll wyll, and loueth both to ſay euyll and do euyll.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked what token is there of the paſes and g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of a man. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:11180:10"/>
               <p> ¶ He that hath large paſes and ſlowe he is auenturous in al thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, and yet he oughte to thynke on that, that is to come, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey to kepe hym ſelfe. And he that hath his paſe haſty and thycke he is wrathfull and of euyll wyll.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Kynge aſked whiche be the beſte tokens to kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we a man by in all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Sydrac. Anſwered.</head>
               <p>¶ He that hath his ſkynne whyte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and ſofte, and that he be not to hye nor to low, nor to great nor to ſmal, and wel melled with why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and red, and his iyen betwene blacke and gray, and that his heed be not to great nor to ſmalle, the necke fayre and ſtreyght and not to longe, and that he haue not to
<pb facs="tcp:11180:10"/>moche fleſſhe on his chynne, nor on his thyes without forth, &amp; that his voyce and ſpeche be clere, and the ſhulders fayre ſtreyght &amp; lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, and the paumes of his handes ſofte, the fyngers longe &amp; ſmalle and that he be of fewe wordes, and that he laught not to moche nor to often, and that he haue a gladſome lokynge / and lyght che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryd, and that he be not to Couey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſe of other mens goodes, and not to aſkynge nor to wernynge. And this is the beſt fygure of man that euer God made. And ſuche mannered &amp; fygured men oughte Kynges and Lordes to haue with them in theyr company, for Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des hath more nede of men, then men haue of Lordes, for Lordes may not be without men, and men may be without Lordes. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore a Kynge oughte to trauayl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11180:11"/>aboute the Lande to drawe ſuche men aboute hym. But he oughte not to be to greatly meued in Iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gement to iudge any man for any token or ſygne that he hathe on hym, but he ought to aſſemble one and other, and deuyde the one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other, and take the beſt and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thoſe that be not vertuous nor of good condicions as ferforth as it may be knowen, for of this ſhall come great profyte &amp; great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and good auenture.</p>
               <trailer>¶ Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners / tokens / and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycions of man. And hereafter foloweth the propertyes of a good Horſe.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise_on_the_horse">
            <pb facs="tcp:11180:11"/>
            <head>¶ The Propertyes of a good Horſe.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of Pegasus and Bellerophon</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>
                  </hi> Good Horſe ſhuld haue .xv. propertyes &amp; condicions. That is to wete, thre of a Man, thre of a Woman, thre of a Foxe, thre of an Hare, &amp; thre of an Aſſe. ¶ Of a man bolde proude and har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye. ¶ Of a woman fayre breſted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fayre of heer, and eaſy to lepe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11180:12"/>
               <p> ¶ Of a Foxe, a fayre tayle ſhorte eres, with a good trotte. ¶ Of an hare a great eye, a dry heed, &amp; well rennynge. ¶ Of an Aſſe a bygge chyn, a flat legge, &amp; a good houe. ¶ Wel trauayled wemen nor wel trauailed horſe, were neuer good. ¶ Aryſe erly. Serue God deuout<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye. And the worlde beſely. Do thy worke wyſely. Gyue thyne almeſſe ſecretly. Go by thy way ſadly. An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere the people demurely. Go to thy meate appetytely. Syt therat dyſcretly. Of thy tonge be not to lyberally. Aryſe therfro temperat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye. Go to thy ſupper ſoberly. And to thy bed merily. Be i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thine Inne Iocundly. Pleaſe thy loue duely. And ſlepe ſurely.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Marke well theſe foure thynges.</head>
               <p>¶ There ben foure thynges pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cypallye to be drad of euery wyſe
<pb facs="tcp:11180:12"/>man. The <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>urſe of our holy father the <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pe. ¶ The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de is the Indygnacion of a prince. (Quia indignatio regis vel principie more eſt.) ¶ The thyrde is the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour or the wil of a Iudge. ¶ The fourth is ſlaunder and the muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of a comynaltie.</p>
               <p>¶ who that maketh in Chryſtmas a dogge to his larder. And in mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che a ſow to his gardiner. And in May a foole of a wyſe mans cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeyle. He ſhall neuer haue good lar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, fayre gardyne, nor yet well kept counſayle.</p>
               <p>¶ Farre from thy kinſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> caſt th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, wrath not thy neyghboures next the, In a good corne cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre threſt the. And ſyt downe Robyn and reſt the.</p>
               <p>¶ There be foure thynges full har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de for to knowe whiche way that they wyl drawe. The fyrſte is the
<pb facs="tcp:11180:13"/>wayes of a y<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an. ¶ The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde is the courſe of a veſſell in the ſee. ¶ The thyrde of an adder or of a ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſpre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. ¶ The fourth of a fowle ſyttynge on any thyng. ¶ <q>
                     <l>Two wyues in one houſe,</l>
                     <l>Two cattes and one mouſe</l>
                     <l>Two dogges and one bone,</l>
                     <l>Shall neuer accorde in one.</l>
                  </q> ¶ Who that manneth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his kyn And cloſeth his croft w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cheritres Shall haue many hegges brokyn And alſo full lytell good ſeruyes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>¶ Finis.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprynted by me Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Wyer: Dwellynge at the Sygne of S. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Euangelyſt / in S. Martyns Paryſſhe beſyde Charynge Croſſe.</p>
            <p>ROBERT <figure>
                  <figDesc>merchant's mark</figDesc>
               </figure> WYER.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11180:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
